<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05389865</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRAS 309277</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05389865</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Proximal Aortopathy in Scotland - Epidemiology and Surgical Outcomes</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Investigation Into the Epidemiology and Surgical Intervention for Proximal Aortic Disease in Scotland</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Golden Jubilee National Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aberdeen Royal Infirmary</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Royal Infirmary of Edinburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Network for Inherited Cardiac Conditions Scotland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Glasgow</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Golden Jubilee National Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aorta is the principal arterial vessel arising from the left heart that transfers blood&#xD;
      to the body. Certain genetic and familial disease processes are known to weaken the aortic&#xD;
      wall resulting in dilation and potential rupture. These aortic complications carry high&#xD;
      mortality (&gt;25%) and current management is orientated towards early detection and preventive&#xD;
      treatment. Aortic dilation can also result in aortic valve dysfunction leading to heart&#xD;
      failure. The estimated UK incidence of aortic disease per year is around 10 per 100,000&#xD;
      individuals, with 2000 people per year dying from aortic complications.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The 2017-2020 National Adult Cardiac Surgery Audit report identified the number of people&#xD;
      receiving surgery for aortic dissection in Scotland is per population proportionately lower&#xD;
      compared to England (4.6 per million per year in Scotland vs. 6.6 per million per year in&#xD;
      England). The reasons for this are unclear but may relate to the prevalence of aortic disease&#xD;
      or a large geographic distribution with compromised access to specialized centres.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Currently surgery is recommended when the aortic diameter exceeds a certain threshold. There&#xD;
      are several types of effective surgical procedures, but there is still limited information on&#xD;
      their long-term outcomes and the advantage of one procedure over another.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The aims of the project are firstly to determine the clinical outcomes of the surgical&#xD;
      procedures that are currently employed in Scotland to treat proximal aortic disease and&#xD;
      secondly to describe the prevalence and distribution of proximal aortic disease within the&#xD;
      Scottish population. The project will be hosted by the Golden Jubilee Research Institute.&#xD;
      Contemporary and retrospective data will be collected from all the Scottish Cardiothoracic&#xD;
      Surgery units which are based in Glasgow, Edinburgh and Aberdeen.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This will be the first study to analyse surgical outcomes for ascending aortic disease in&#xD;
      Scotland, and the first to describe the epidemiology of aortic disease within the population.&#xD;
      It is anticipated that the results will guide current surgical practise, and provide data to&#xD;
      inform national service provision for the management of proximal aortic disease.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study has two principal aims:&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. Determine the patient demographics, procedural types and related clinical outcomes in&#xD;
           patients who underwent surgery of the proximal thoracic aorta in Scotland&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. Describe the epidemiology of proximal aortopathy within the Scottish population, by&#xD;
           determining the prevalence of disease, geographic distribution and patient demographics&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study will be the first to look at outcomes from a nation-wide cohort of patients&#xD;
      following surgery of the thoracic aorta in the UK. The investigators anticipate that results&#xD;
      from this study will inform future aortic practice and guide decisions on intervention timing&#xD;
      and type.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Information on the prevalence and geographic distribution of aortic disease within Scotland&#xD;
      will guide resource allocation and service configuration to allow equity in access to&#xD;
      treatment. By raising awareness among the medical professionals and the wider community, the&#xD;
      study should lead to improved recognition and better outcomes for patients with aortic&#xD;
      disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Data will be recorded in a contemporary and retrospective manner for two patient cohorts:&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. Surgical cohort - Adult patients who have had a surgical intervention on the proximal&#xD;
           aorta in the three Scottish Cardiothoracic Surgery units based in Glasgow, Edinburgh,&#xD;
           Aberdeen in the last 13 years (2008 - 2021).&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. Non-surgical cohort - Adult patients who have a diagnosis of proximal aortopathy, but&#xD;
           have not had surgery. This cohort will be obtained from three sources:&#xD;
&#xD;
             1. Patients with a diagnosis of thoracic aortopathy identified via National Interim&#xD;
                Clinical Imaging Procedure (NICIP) codes sourced from the Scottish Radiology&#xD;
                Information System (RIS) and Picture Archive and Communication System (PACS)&#xD;
                databases.&#xD;
&#xD;
             2. Patients with a diagnosis of thoracic aortopathy identified from regional genetic&#xD;
                services via the Network for Inherited Cardiac Conditions Scotland.&#xD;
&#xD;
             3. Deceased patients diagnosed with proximal thoracic aortopathy or a complication&#xD;
                thereof (aortic dissection, aortic rupture) registered at death certification&#xD;
                and/or post mortem accessed from Public Health Scotland using ICD-10 codes.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The three data collection sites will be the Golden Jubilee National Hospital in Glasgow, the&#xD;
      Edinburgh Royal Infirmary and Aberdeen Royal Infirmary.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The surgical cohort sample size is expected to be around 1300 patients. The non-surgical&#xD;
      cohort is difficult to estimate, but around 500 cases yearly are expected to be identified.&#xD;
      The research project will be hosted by the NHS Golden Jubilee Research Department.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The principal investigator (George Gradinariu) will undertake this research project as part&#xD;
      of an postgraduate research programme (MD degree) at the University of Glasgow under the&#xD;
      supervision of Professor Mark Danton (Congenital Cardiac Surgeon with interest in proximal&#xD;
      aortic surgery), Professor Alex McConnachie Professor of Biostatistics, University of&#xD;
      Glasgow) and Professor Faisal Ahmed (Samson Gemmell Chair of Child Health, University of&#xD;
      Glasgow)&#xD;
&#xD;
      Statistical analysis will be overseen and supervised by Professor McConnachie. Descriptive&#xD;
      statistics will be applied. Survival data will be analysed using Kaplan-Meier. Multivariable&#xD;
      survival and logistic regression models will be used to identify variables predicting the&#xD;
      risk of adverse outcomes. Predictive modelling to estimate the risk of adverse outcomes based&#xD;
      on aortic root dimension will be assessed using ROC analysis. In comparing survival by&#xD;
      procedures propensity matching will be used to minimize confounding. Analysis will be&#xD;
      performed using R statistical analysis software (R Foundation for Statistical Computing,&#xD;
      Vienna, Austria).&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Early survival following surgery of the proximal aorta</measure>
    <time_frame>In-hospital or 30 days (whichever is longer)</time_frame>
    <description>In-hospital or 30 days survival following surgery of the proximal aorta</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Late survival following surgery of the proximal aorta</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years or latest available follow-up (whichever is longer)</time_frame>
    <description>Long-term survival following surgery of the proximal aorta</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient demographics and geographic distribution of thoracic aortopathy within the Scottish population</measure>
    <time_frame>Cross-sectional analysis (2011-2021)</time_frame>
    <description>Identify the demographics (age, gender, relevant risk factors) and geographic distribution (area codes) of patients diagnosed with thoracic aortopathy within the Scottish population</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular reintervention</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year or latest available follow-up (whichever is longer)</time_frame>
    <description>Reinterventions (surgical/endovascular) related to the aortic implant or unoperated aorta Reintervention on Aortic valve (native or prosthesis)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Specified adverse events following surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year or latest available follow-up (whichever is longer)</time_frame>
    <description>episodes of endocarditis, structural valve degeneration, thromboembolism, cerebral vascular accident, anticoagulant-related bleeding</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) following surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year or latest available follow-up (whichever is longer)</time_frame>
    <description>Long-term left ventricular ejection fraction (&gt;50% - good, 31-50% - moderate, 21-30% - poor, 20% or less -very poor) as measured by echocardiography or cardiac MRI after surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Aortic valve mean gradient and degree of regurgitation following surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year or latest available follow-up (whichever is longer)</time_frame>
    <description>Long-term aortic valve function as assessed by mean gradient (mmHg) and degree of regurgitation (mild/moderate/severe) in operated patients assessed by echocardiography or cardiac MRI</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Genotypes and phenotypes prevalent in the Scottish population</measure>
    <time_frame>Previous 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Identify genotypes and phenotypes in the Scottish population and assess their prevalence</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2000</enrollment>
  <condition>Aortic Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Aortic Dissection</condition>
  <condition>Aortic Aneurysm, Thoracic</condition>
  <condition>Aortic Ectasia</condition>
  <condition>Aortic Valve Insufficiency</condition>
  <condition>Bicuspid Aortic Valve</condition>
  <condition>Marfan Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Loeys-Dietz Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>Adult patients (18 years of age and above) who have had a surgical intervention on the proximal aorta in the three Scottish Cardiothoracic Surgery units based in Glasgow, Edinburgh, Aberdeen.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-surgical cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>- Adult patients (18 years of age and above) who have a diagnosis of proximal aortopathy, but have not had surgical intervention (non-surgical/un-intervened proximal aortopathy). This cohort will be obtained from three sources:&#xD;
Scottish national radiological database based on specific imaging codes&#xD;
Regional genetic/inherited cardiac conditions services&#xD;
Public Health Scotland via specific diagnostic ICD-10 codes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Surgery on the proximal aorta (aortic root +/- ascending aorta)</intervention_name>
    <description>Surgery involving replacing, repairing or reinforcing the proximal aorta (root and ascending aorta)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Patients diagnosed with thoracic aortopathy but not operated upon</intervention_name>
    <description>Radiological size criteria or Genetic mutations associated with aortopathies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non-surgical cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        1. Surgical cohort (Observational cohort design)- Adult patients (18 years of age and&#xD;
             above) who have had a surgical intervention on the proximal aorta in the three&#xD;
             Scottish Cardiothoracic Surgery units based in Glasgow, Edinburgh, Aberdeen.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Non-surgical cohort (Cross-sectional design) - Adult patients (18 years of age and&#xD;
             above) who have a diagnosis of proximal aortopathy, but have not had surgical&#xD;
             intervention (non-surgical/un-intervened proximal aortopathy). This cohort will be&#xD;
             obtained from three sources:&#xD;
&#xD;
               1. Scottish national radiological database based on specific imaging codes&#xD;
&#xD;
               2. Regional genetic/inherited cardiac conditions services&#xD;
&#xD;
               3. Public Health Scotland via specific diagnostic ICD-10 codes.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Surgical cohort&#xD;
&#xD;
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  all adults (&gt;18 years of age) that underwent surgical intervention on the proximal&#xD;
             aorta in Scotland between 2008 and 2021.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Isolated surgery on the descending thoracic aorta&#xD;
&#xD;
        Non-surgical cohort&#xD;
&#xD;
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
        - all adult patients (&gt;18 years of age) with a radiological, genetic or post-mortem&#xD;
        diagnosis of thoracic aortic disease&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>George Gradinariu, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Golden Jubilee National Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>George Gradinariu, MD</last_name>
    <phone>01419515000</phone>
    <email>george.gradinariu2@nhs.scot</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 6, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 21, 2022</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 25, 2022</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 6, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 6, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 9, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Golden Jubilee National Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>George Gradinariu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator, Cardiothoracic Surgery Specialty Registrar</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>aortic surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>aortic root</keyword>
  <keyword>ascending aorta</keyword>
  <keyword>surgical outcomes</keyword>
  <keyword>thoracic aortopathy epidemiology</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Marfan Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arachnodactyly</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Loeys-Dietz Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aortic Aneurysm</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aneurysm, Dissecting</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bicuspid Aortic Valve Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aortic Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aortic Valve Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aortic Aneurysm, Thoracic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>To apply for further studies, beyond the current research, using the existing dataset, a research proposal submitted to the GJNH Research Department will be required. This will follow the established internal peer-review process established by the GJNH research department. If approved, a data request form will need to be submitted to the data custodian who will release the pseudo- anonymised data to the research applicant. If there is no request to extend the study then this data will be deleted.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

